[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
dot org slash software for software
engineering radio this is Robert bloomin
today I have with me fen jinyang engine
is a lead engineer at Metamarkets
here's a graduate of the University of
Waterloo in electrical engineering and
has an advanced degree in computer
engineering
prior to Metamarkets engine worked at
Cisco Ericsson and juniper he's one of
the creators of the druid real-time
analytical data store and is the author
of a research paper on this topic which
was published in the Proceedings of the
ACM sigmod International Conference on
data management today fens and I will be
talking about real-time analytics and
the druid data store Benjen welcome to
software engineering radio Robert thanks
for having me excited to be here I'm
really excited to do this show also
we've had a lot of shows on data storage
but only a fraction of them on analytics
so I'd like to talk first about the area
of analytic data stores and then we can
proceed to situating druid within that
space and what makes it what its niche
is within that space how does that sound
that's great okay so the term OLAP very
common label within this space can we
start out with what was your view of
OLAP and how's it distinguished from
other activities within the general
umbrella of querying data sure so a lot
stands for online analytical processing
and I believe the term was initially
conceived as a contrast to OLTP which is
online transactional processing and Olaf
generally refers to business
intelligence stall queries so it's this
whole idea of understanding trends
in your data and the workflow often
involves sort of like aggregates so with
olaf workflows you typically have event
or log based data and you're trying to
compute like sums for example sums of
revenues sums of other key metrics that
you care about broken down by like
attributes or dimensions of the data so
for example sums of you know how much
revenue was generated for a particular
product for a particular user
demographic at a particular location
with a lot of pollock workflows you're
really just trying to break down break
down a larger data set and understand
trends within that data set great
reading about this I found some key
concepts that are very much discussed
that I'd like you to explain the first
one is the idea of a cube or hypercube
right so OLAP has kind of traditionally
modelled data in this idea of a alot
tube and the whole idea behind the cube
is it's supposed to be multi-dimensional
so you can think of the edges of the
cube representing like attributes your
data for example like the product name
or the location and different faces of
the cube are representing like different
views of the data and typically you know
a face of the cube will show some set of
data some sort of like aggregate values
for data broken down by the dimensions
which are the edges of the cube with
most real-world data set you can have
many many different dimensions in your
data and you can have incredibly complex
multi-dimensional cubes so one I guess
terminology that people refer to these
complex multi-dimensional cubes is like
hyper cubes let's give an example here
you started out with the idea of product
and wood dimensions be things like the
store that sold it the date when it was
sold total value of the transaction am I
going in the right direction yeah
absolutely
so I guess with OLAP workflows the sort
of traditional way of characterizing
data is you have a set of dimensions
and you have a set of measures or
metrics so measures and metrics they
tend to be numeric in nature and they
refer to things like revenue or count
they're fertile egg number of products
sold things that you like want to add up
basically and there's a whole lot of
other ways to define your data and these
are fertilized dimensions and attributes
so there are things like the product
name potentially like a city where the
product was sold the time is often a
dimension that's part of OLAP workflows
so you know for every product that's
sold you record when it was sold record
where was sold you know how much it was
sold for and anything else you can tag
along with that sale I've run across
this concept of these dimensions
existing at different levels of
granularity example time could be year
month day could you explain that role of
these different granularities
in the OLAP cube right so with
dimensions oftentimes they're sort of
like a hierarchy that can exist within
dimension and this is sort of like a
natural way to classify data for example
you can have a hierarchy where you have
like a country and you have a state you
have a city and you might have like a
particular neighborhood within the city
similarly as you mentioned with time you
know there's like year there's month
Thursday and the way you sort of
structure this data is directly
correlated to the types of queries you
want to make with this data often when
you're making business intelligence
queries you want to understand you know
how revenue changed on potentially a
daily basis or a quarterly basis or a
yearly basis or the span of like many
years and you may also want do
comparisons with different time
granularities so this this hierarchy is
kind of a way of like narrowing down
your exploration of data and also
widening your exploration of data
suppose I have time as a dimension I
know when every product was sold down to
the minute I might be interested in
looking at
as you're seeing trends over month year
week but is it the case that all the raw
data is still there in the cube down to
whatever level of granularity it was
originally collected and I can pop up or
down levels as I think of new questions
so I think the answer to that really
depends on sort of the infrastructure
that you are using to explore data with
certain infrastructures you may only
have certain time buckets available with
different infrastructures you may have
like arbitrary time buckets available
all the way down to the raw data that
you know first generated so with a lot
of like modern I guess analytic systems
which are derived from key value stores
that level of like arbitrary data
expiration is not necessarily available
with other systems it is so really
depends on what you're using ok I think
you hinted at this briefly there are two
or three primary types of queries in
OLAP known as roll-up drill down and
slicing please explain what those are
right so I guess traditional role of
sorry traditional OLAP has role up drill
down slice and dice and pivot I believe
as the the main ones and all these
queries are effectively defining how to
explore your data for example I've
always thought this drill down as
narrowing down your data for example if
you go back to that hierarchy of
dimensions and the time exploration that
we talked about before when you explore
by year and you now want to explore by
month or by day you're drilling down
into your data and similarly if you're
exploring by minute and you all kind of
want a wider view of your data you want
to explore by day or by month or by year
you're effectively rolling up your data
and then slicing and dicing is this
whole idea of basically breaking down
your data and looking at
filtered views of your data so in our
you know in a very simple sales database
you may only want to know how many sales
were generated in the city of San
Francisco in that case you are looking
at a very specific narrow down view of
your data and your slicing your data
based on a single dimension the dice
term generally refers to having more
than one dimension so if you want to
know how much revenue was generated in
the city of San Francisco where the
users also male that's an example of
incorporating just two dimensions and
still filtering down your your view of
the data we start out with a
multi-dimensional cube that could have
50 dimensions I'm doing a query how many
dimensions do I get back in the query
result and how do I see the query result
right so with OLAP workflows I guess the
sort of key point with Oh lock workflows
is when people have a data set with like
50 dimensions when the issue queries
against that data set they almost never
care about like all 50 dimensions with a
lot of OLAP queries you don't really
care about like a single row in the data
you also don't care about the entire
data set what you almost always care
about is some filtered view of your
total data so you may care about you
know a total set of aggregates over time
which is like one dimension or you might
care about a total set of aggregates
with time and a handful of other
dimensions mixed in in very rare cases
and I never see them in in the real
world where you care about all 50
dimensions and like some crazy
combination of all 50 dimensions is
usually a handful like less than 10 okay
so I might care about my product sales
growth over time by month and I also
want to see it broken down by state and
maybe by whether the shoppers male or
female right okay and he's there are
there so I've named four dimensions if I
was counting correctly are there decent
visualizations that could show me that
four dimensional variability so I think
the the short answer to
that question is yes there are decent
visualizations the visualization like if
you know exactly what you are querying
for it is like there's plenty of systems
out there that can sort of Jenner
generate a visualization for your
particular query I'm having trouble
answering the question beyond that
beyond a very simple answer of yes there
are like visualizations if you like know
what you're querying for
I guess the pivot table is an example of
such a visualization which kind of
allows you to break down your data by
multiple dimensions and give you like a
filtered view that's fairly easy to
understand most analytic products offer
some pivot table some form of a pivot
table for your look at more meaningful
visualizations beyond that I'm actually
not too sure ok fair enough
now you introduced the term pivot table
and I need to ask for an explanation of
that because not familiar with that so I
guess you can think of a pivot table as
a interactive way of being able to
explore the different phases of an OLAP
cube hmm
so it's a way of breaking down it's a
way of like for example you want to look
at how your products are selling in
different cities and you want to rotate
that cube and you I want to know like
how your products are selling across
like different time quarters so you
rotate across the cube and you're always
presented with like different views of
data and people have like productized
this in effectively a table where you
can kind of specify how you want to
drill down into you how you want to
filter and drill down into your cube
that's get the results that you care
about okay I'd like to move on a bit to
one of the differentiating terms in the
drip product which is real-time as a
preface to that let's talk about if I
didn't say real-time I just said
analytic data store what makes it not
real-time or what does that base case
look like and then then I'm going to ask
you how to
is a real-time change that right um I
guess I can start off with explaining
what my thoughts are on real-time I'm an
engineer so I always feel like real-time
is a buzz word much like big data or
like cloud or anything
these other buzzwords that are out there
and that you know every company's
offering it but it's really unclear like
what is actually being offered and it
means something completely different to
everyone out there
broadly speaking real-time is this whole
idea of being able to explore your data
on events as they're happening not
several hours after they've occurred
that's what it's always meant for me and
what sort of real-time enables is it
enables a faster feedback loop for
decision-making
one of the main used cases I've seen for
you know so-called
real-time analytic tools is the ability
to like alert when there's a spike in
our data or there's like a drop in some
metric so as we're able to explore
events closer and closer to when they
actually occur we can start building
much smarter decision systems that react
as soon as some event occurs so the
second part of your question I believe
was around like real-time in Druid let's
come back to that effect so that was
fine okay ah someone has a different
question
yeah from looking at my product sales
trends by month yep then if I could have
that be up to the date within the last
minute or five seconds it probably
wouldn't change anything substantive so
there must be a different set of
problems where it would make a change in
your final decision to have really
updated information so what are some of
the problem domains where this is an
advantage so going back to sort of I
guess that sales model
OLAP model you can imagine a case where
your revenue is like pretty constant and
it's up to the most five seconds and all
of a sudden there's like a gigantic drop
in revenue and that gigantic drop is
usually indicative of something like
incredibly
wrong with your system or with your your
sales process and being able to see that
drop instantaneously and alerting your
your organization and be able to react
on that change to mean that you can fix
a potentially like gigantic problem in
your system very very quickly versus
seeing that drop like several days or
day after its occurred and then by that
time a lot more damage could have been
done in your organization would be fair
to say then that the real-time
application is more of interest to UPS
or systems people where the higher
timescale aggregations are more for
business I think that's very fair this
is I think one of the first use cases
that I've seen and that alerts and being
notified of significant changes in your
system is you know is incredibly
important but I also believe that
decisions can be made on real-time
systems for example if you have revenue
and you're sort of watching the trend
growth of revenue and once revenue
breaks like a certain threshold then
some actions like your system
automatically take some action I think
this is a use case that a lot of people
out there have been thinking of I
haven't seen it that much in practice I
see the ops use case much more so in
practice but I believe as these
real-time systems mature more
intelligent decision-making will also
like follow the business intelligence it
exists in order to provide business
people with data for them to understand
their business and and make the seasons
this case you just now described it
sounds like the analytics tool is a
piece but not the terminal piece in your
organization's data pipelines and
workflows where it surfaces interesting
aggregates that then feed into the next
piece in the workflow is that where this
is going where it's no longer so much of
a human facing tool as the old bi that's
what I tend to believe I believe there's
sort of an evolution with analytic
systems in that in the very beginning
of these data warehouses you had
analysts which would query systems and
you know results returned in several
hours and they would create reports and
send it off to decision-makers to
analyze and as systems got more powerful
then you saw more like direct
applications on top of like data
warehouses where you had entire
applications that are driven by data and
centered around like data exploration
and I guess I see for the next phase of
so it sort of the general trend there is
systems for getting faster and decisions
are getting faster as well and so the
next phase is there's more automation
that's incorporated and there's
decisions that are that are made on the
fly and I've seen systems out there
where the analytic system makes a
decision to sort of like feeds it off
into some other system for like further
processing and at least I believe that
alig systems in the future will be a lot
more like hands off wow that's
fascinating
we had Nathan Mart's on recently talking
about spark he discussed a buzzword
which we're hearing all these days of
the lamda architecture where there's of
the slow leg and the fast leg yep
it's this real-time analytic space
another name for the fast leg of the
lamda architecture uh yeah definitely so
sort of the the whole idea behind the
lamda architecture is you have sort of a
speed layer where you can view insights
into your data right away and you also
have this accompanying batch pipeline
which can potentially do cleanups that
exist from errors in your speed layer if
you look at the current state of open
source stream app stream for structure
streaming infrastructure and I'm talking
about like Kafka and Sam's on storm and
many others out there not all of them
provide like exactly once guarantees
with data in that duplication of events
is something that may occur every now
and then and it's very difficult to
guarantee a perfect pipeline with
screaming
only data but you know there are a lot
of advantages to having slight slight
inaccuracies in our data if you can see
like insights in your data right away so
sort of to for use cases which require
like absolute accuracy of data you also
have this batch pipeline which you know
goes in and kind of like cleans up data
and fixes it up but like that batch
pipeline usually runs no many hours
slower than your so-called real-time
pipeline like to turn now to the druid
system let's start at the top with a
high-level description of what what is
druid and what particular problem does
it solve right the Sony buffers to
choose from so druid is a data store or
its infrastructure that's primarily
designed for analytics and the main
value add of druid or like the two
things that druid focuses on a lot is
the latency in which you can ingest data
so the latency you can get data into the
system and the latency you can answer
queries so the latency that you can get
data out of the system and what we've
seen with the druid and how it's been
adopted is the primary use case the
primary value add up druid is it
provides exploratory analytics and it's
able to power applications it's able to
power data analytic applications at
scale let's go a little bit into that
term exploratory tell us more about that
right so by exploratory analytics I mean
like druid is an OLAP store so it
provides the ability to slice and dice
and issue ad hoc queries ad hoc roll-up
or drill down queries and effectively it
gives a user the ability to kind of
break down their data however they want
so if you build an application on top of
druid a lot of the applications we've
seen kind of give the user the ability
to fully explore the data however they
want and then the other leg of that
description was power applications at
scale say bit more about that um right
so what we've seen happen in the last
few years is
is a lot of organizations are preferring
to explore and interact with their data
through applications as it goes back
this whole idea where in the past we had
sort of analysts issuing you know sequel
queries and queries to this data
back-end and in getting results like
hours later what we see more often these
days is we see applications where a user
doesn't have to be extremely technical
to be able to interact with the data and
Drude is built with this idea that we
want to make it easy for people to build
these types of applications that
interact with the data and in particular
we want people to build applications
that still feel really snappy and give
users a really good experience when
there's a ton of data that needs to be
analyzed let's set up a sample
application that you think is a very
typical or great use case for Druid what
is the overall structure of that system
in word is Druid fit in the architecture
and the high level topology so I guess
there's a couple of different ways to
answer that question I can answer it in
the terms of you know what do sort of
analytic stacks out there look like and
where does Drouet fit in or I could
answer that question in terms of like
what are the types of applications
people are building and like where does
Druid fit in and I was wondering like
which direction yeah let's talk about
some of the more popular types of
applications and where Druid fits into
those applicants sure so the types of
applications people build they're always
center around event data or time series
data you know some event occurs and this
event has a set of attributes and it has
a set of like metrics and you want to do
like OLAP queries on many many of these
events Druid kind of fits in the role of
the database that you would be you would
be querying directly so your application
issues a set of queries directly to
druid and Android returns the results
and similarly you might have event data
that gets loaded directly into druid it
could be streamed in a queue loaded
versus VI a batch process
what are some examples of the event data
producing domains like protecting log
files or securities prices or what right
I can talk about the datasets I've seen
it is pretty popular in ad tech because
it was initially developed for an ad
type use case it was developed at an ad
tech startup called Metamarkets
so where I still work so you know when
Metamarkets goes and talks about druid a
lot of ACTA companies notice so with AD
tech data pretty popular there we've
seen it now get adopted for like
operations use cases for example like
systems operations monitoring collecting
systems logs and doing analytics and
aggregations with on top of system logs
I've seen it get picked up in network
analysis so people can feed like people
trying tract packets through a system
and then feed information about that
into druid we've also have use cases and
I guess the internet of things from like
devices emitting events and collecting
that information doing Alex on top of
that we've also seen like interest now
in finance as well those these cases I
like their more recent so I understand
them less than the at Tech operations
network analysis use cases let's look at
ad tech a little bit then what are the
incoming records and fields or
dimensions and what is the question that
ad Tech is using druid to answer right
so within at Tech there's a space called
real-time bidding and basically what
happens there is you can think of every
time you visit a webpage there's ads
that show up on this webpage but in the
milliseconds from when you click on a
link to when a webpage appears there's
actually a pretty sophisticated process
that's occurring behind the scenes where
a whole bunch of different systems are
trying to programmatically outbid each
other in order to display you an ad and
when you're on that web page there's a
whole lot of information that's being
collected on what you're what you're
actually doing on that web page and all
this information is in the it generates
events so an event might be like
person X with a certain set of
demographics on a certain webpage with a
certain set of attributes has viewed an
ad and later on another event might
occur which is person X has now clicked
on this ad and now every time someone
looks at an ad you can imagine this is
you know a web page like Facebook or
Google where a lot of people are looking
at ads and a lot of people are also
clicking on ads and being able to track
and analyze all that data then is it if
I see the direction you're going you'd
want to find some kind of aggregation
say people like the guy who's about to
see an ad are more likely to open the ad
if it matches up on dimensions a B and C
right that's that's one of the use cases
a common use case is like you know how
much revenue was generated by males from
18 to 49 for example on Facebook comm
and how does that compare to you know
kids in high school like what what is
the revenue difference there what about
the revenue difference on a picture like
location how does the Bay Area compare
it to like the East Coast like those
types of questions and try to understand
why people are clicking on ads and where
the revenue from ad clicks is is coming
from the answers to those questions are
they substantially different if they're
based on instantaneously up-to-date data
versus data that's only updated every
few hours or once a day but I think
that's a really great question I
actually don't know the answer to that
question because I actually have very
limited understanding about tech I kind
of focus a lot more on the technology I
would imagine that the answer to that is
it does not differ substantially based
on whether it's like right now versus
some time in the past hmm okay well that
gives us a good idea of what druid is
and where it sits in the system I can
talk a little bit about sort of the
general space of big data infrastructure
and sort of the different solutions out
there and like we're kind of trade fits
in that as well um I want to go more
into druid
so sure there's some really interesting
stuff yeah there where the challenges
that you faced as create for creating a
real-time OLAP that the batch OLAP
solutions do not face right so I guess
the biggest challenge that is faced with
building a real real time elapsed tour
is being able to ingest a very high
volume of data while still being able to
answer queries on top of that data and
being able to understand the resources
that get used and providing stability
when there's potentially like spikes in
volume of the data for a minute or so
which is the somewhat common use case
with a pure batch system against taking
a step back druid is deals with mostly
append-only data mostly append-only and
it generates like immutable views over
that data so when you batch load data
into druid it's very simple in that you
just generate immutable views of your
batch data but when you have real-time
data coming in you know it's obviously
not immutable because the beds are cost
me being appended on and if it requires
a little bit more thinking in in dealing
with a high volume of immutable data
versus batches of immutable data if that
makes sense
in mind I'd like to drill down more into
the internal architecture of druid and
then you could explain what happens when
high rate of data streams in where it
goes so at a high level what are the
main internal components of a druid
system so a druid cluster I mean druid
is a distributed system it's comprised
of many different types of nodes and
actually each node is each node type is
designed to do a particular set of
things very well
so there's nodes which are dedicated for
like coordination and like load
balancing there are nodes which are
dedicated to
chillie for historical data and there
are nodes which are dedicated
particularly for like real-time or
streaming data
I guess there's there's two aspects of
Druid architecture that we talk about we
can talk about the architecture of the
overall system and the the roles at the
different nodes play and we can also
talk about the like the format in which
data is stored and then it's yeah we can
go in either direction there let's start
out with the different types of nodes
and what role they play ok so the
simplest Drude cluster comprises of
three types of nodes there's a set of
historical nodes and basically
historical nodes are they're pretty
simple they load like immutable blocks
of data and in Druid these immutable
blocks are called segments a segment is
basically it contains data for a
particular time range in a particular
structure and historical knows they know
how to load segments they know how to
answer queries on segments and they know
how to like drop segments so their
operation is pretty simple and in front
of the historical notes for queries
there is a set of broker nodes and
broker nodes they encapsulate like query
scattered gathered functionality so if
you as a users and the query for like
you know give me the aggregates for this
this one week this one weeks worth of
data might be partitioned into seven
different segments and in our example
we're imagining like one segment
contains data for one day so the broker
says ok I have a query for seven
segments and these seven segments might
live on like X number of historical
nodes so it kind of fans the query out
to the store connotes the historical
nodes compute their portion of the
answer in parallel and return results of
the broker and the broker returns to the
actual caller so it you know the broker
is doing the scanner gather
functionality and struggle nodes
you know they follow a shared nothing
architecture doing computations and the
other type of node there is like a
coordinator node and the coordinator
node is responsible for telling
historicals when to load new data and
when to drop new data so it can say like
circle one you know
move segment from you to historical
three and it does that in order for like
load-balanced so there's lot of
coordination load-balancing activity
that the coordinator nodes handle right
and to extend beyond that architecture
then you have like real-time nodes which
is only handling data for like a very
small window and what real-time nodes do
is they collect you know streaming data
and they periodically convert that data
into like the immutable form so though
they snapshot and create an immutable
view of the data they've collected for a
small window of time and then hand that
data off to the historical nodes so you
have this constant handoff process
occurring and the real time notes are
all always dealing with a small window
of recent incoming data I imagine in any
business query on any system that time
is an important dimension it sounds to
me like you've chosen to make time the
primary dimension in the architecture of
the system right so right now time is a
very special dimension in Druid we've
always talked about time being
potentially a less special dimension as
you imagine like most OLAP works you
know with most OLAP data modeling time
is just one of the dimensions it's not
special more special than any other
dimension for a lot of sort of
simplicity and development volume
development velocity we've kind of made
time a really special dimension and
we've said that all data that goes into
Druid must have a timestamp we
additionally always partition data based
on time so when we have a lot of data we
might create you know we might partition
of data by day or by hour or potentially
by some smaller interval makes sense to
me that something that's calling itself
real time that promises to have special
behaviors around time will ultimately be
forced to treat time in that way I don't
know do you agree or disagree yes so for
the time being definitely I agree that
time is really special to do it and I
think for a while time will always be
really special
druid and we'll make a lot of decisions
based on this like time field I think it
is possible to ultimately have a system
in which time is not like not any more
special than any other dimension while
still maintaining the same sort of
guarantees that we have right now well
be interesting to keep watch out for
that but talk a little bit in relation
to the architecture that you just
described how does druid support roll up
and drill down when someone issues a
query what is what is druid do to serve
the results right so I guess the best
way to answer that question is to talk
about how druid is actually storing the
results and drew it is a column-oriented
database and every column is stored
individually so with when you issue a
query against druid effectively only the
columns which are addressed in the query
are needed to answer the query and you
know drew it is with all home databases
it's better than row stores for like
loading and scanning exactly what you
need with druid you sort of have the
ability in your in your results to
bucket the results in some in some time
granularity for example you can have
results returned on you know on a
permanent basis or on a per hour basis
on a per day basis and druid will will
go in and it will pull up the time
column and pull up a metric column and
it will scan those columns and aggregate
or summarize those results and then
stick it in one of the buckets does that
sort of make sense yes the buckets you
determine what time granularity you want
the results and so you know in advance
what the approximately what the
appearance of the results will be and
then you just fill up those buckets yes
effective okay you make answer columns
and then populating buckets as you're
scanning through those columns right
okay this druid have its own query
language yes it does
druids cray language right now is json
over a cv so you basically if
ooh a blob of JSON VI like a post call
and the results return to you in a JSON
format as well people have built sort of
different adapters are different query
layers on top of Druids native query
language sequel is something that the
community has contributed there's also
query clients that are written in Python
and are and other languages pretty much
whatever language you want yeah pretty
much writing what they saw by hand is an
absolute pain when I was reading about
OLAP I found some of the products are
based on sequel and and some of them are
not this is not specifically a Dredd
question how do you see the relationship
between OLAP and the sequel language
there was this whole no sequel movement
and there are many popular sort of no
sequel stores out there so sequel still
sort of remains to the facto standard
for how you query a database and one
thing we've kind of seen withdrew it and
I imagine like other databases that
don't support sequel ultimately face is
that when people want to build
applications when teams want to build
applications the developers don't
necessarily want to learn a new language
to be able to query this data store they
just want to use equal and that's what
they know and oftentimes you know they
have an existing application already and
they want to migrate from like a legacy
system onto a newer potentially more
scalable system and as part of that
migration they don't want to rewrite the
entire like query interface effectively
so you know sequel I think will still be
around for quite a while yet and we see
a ton of requests on Druid for sequel
support and ultimately like the
community just had to contribute it
because of how you know how much it was
requested you just now mentioned the
community and that leads into another
area I want to ask you about the grid is
an open source project talk about how
did it become open-source and what is
the community like right so sort of the
history of Druitt is it was it was
initially created at Metamarkets an
engineer there called Eric Tedder
started actually the first lines of
druid I joined him very early into
Druids lifetime and we worked basically
side-by-side to build this project out
and we built it for a lot of like
Metamarkets is use cases which is better
market had a data application centered
around exploring ad tech data and we
tried a whole bunch of different systems
and the systems didn't really meet our
needs so we started building out through
it and as we built this thing and as we
started using it we kind of realized
that druid has application beyond just
ad tech and the system that we use could
potentially benefit the wider community
I think it's as an engineer you
invariably just end up using a lot of
open-source technologies and a lot of
technology stacks at companies like ours
and many others out there are comprised
of many different open-source
technologies so we really wanted to like
contribute back to you know the open
source community we've taken so much
from it we want to give something back
and we open-source through it after we
were developing it in-house for about
two years it's kind of nice to see that
has indeed gotten picked up for some
different use cases and it's adding
value to people out there if I
understood you correctly said the
community has contributed a sequel
adapter and is that right yeah the
community has actually contributed all
manners of like really interesting stuff
you know true in the relative scope of
things is a pretty like young
open-source project so we're very much
still building out our community but
what the committee has contributed back
like the sequel one is pretty big
but they've also contributed like core
druid functionality as well well which
is really cool and contribution comes in
many different ways so the community
they ask questions they file bugs they
write Docs so it's pretty cool to see do
any other add-ons or extensions that
come to mind that you think of as being
very original and and and showing a
aspect of grid that you might not have
thought of not of ourselves yeah
community I actually know of that I know
of some pretty unique like approximate
algorithms that other organizations have
built on top of druid I don't think
they're open-source yet
but from my understanding is they're
going to be open source like pretty
shortly
it's cleaned up a little bit more so
there are definitely use cases from like
research teams at organize at different
organizations that we've never thought
about and we hope that more of like
these types of things are going to come
out in the next few months to few years
one ask a little bit about size and
scaling issues you're talking about
large data ingestion rates what is a
large input stream and and what is a
large data set for a drug cluster to
manage right so I can talk about some of
the existing clusters I know one of the
largest single clusters is at meadow
markets where Drude was born and there
we are ingesting at half a million
events per second on average right now
and each event has maybe about 30 to 50
dimensions and like maybe 20 or so
metrics and the total size of that
cluster is I think the last count was
around 50 petabytes of raw data and with
all the different compression and
roll-up algorithms that we throw on top
of that data it gets down to maybe about
300 350 terabytes or so of like query
board druid data so that's sort of the
largest cluster that I know of Yahoo is
a pretty big user of druid and I think
the cumulative size of their clusters
might exceed the largest one of
Metamarkets but I don't have those
numbers so there are some pretty big
ones out there I don't actually one
startup out there I think they're
ingestion rates are over a million
events per second and but I like I don't
know the exact number of dimensions or
metrics they have per event and do you
have a guess of 4 million event per
second cluster how many nodes how many
total cores are there in a cluster that
size right so it really I think heavily
depends on the exact nature of the event
and sort of the the calculations you
want to do with that event the more
complex the more dimensions or metrics
an event has the slower it is to ingest
what we've seen is we've typically seen
maybe 10 or 20,000 events per second per
node I guess it's really per core but
it's often per note as well that can
vary like dramatically depending on the
complexity of the event if you have very
simple events we've done as high as
almost a million events per second with
you know a better set of dimensions and
metrics but like with realistic with
realistic data it's about twenty
thousand ish 10 to 20,000 to 30,000
that's per second per node okay and at
the other end of the size and complexity
scale if the developer wants to set it
up on their workstation you described a
number of different types of nodes and
where you need my sequins ooh keeper
what's the workflow for getting it to
run on your workstation right
so yeah druid is I think probably one of
the more complex systems out there to
setup it has a dependency on a metadata
store so that's either my sequel or
Postgres or the two popular ones hesita
pendency on zookeeper for distributed
coordination and has all these different
types of nodes you know we're always
trying to make it simpler we recently
added like docker script which you can
you know it's sort of like a one-click
spin up an entire cluster on your local
box for like development or POC purposes
if you're doing like a full-blown
trigger cluster for production our
thinking has always been like well most
your cluster is going to be like a store
IKONOS or like real-time nodes and you
only need like two coordinator nodes and
you know the coordination notes you need
very few of them and need a lot of like
query processing nodes so in that sense
all these having all these different
types of nodes is not so bad
but when you're like just looking at it
for the first time it can be daunting to
see oh man there's like so many
different nodes that's like think about
it manage but hopefully make that
process easier and sort of the
nondescript is a start yeah I can see
that we're getting close to the end of
our time were there any issues about des
rid or OLAP that you would like to get
in that I haven't asked you about I
think the most interesting set of issues
that we're thinking about right now and
kind of maybe phases the entire data
analytics community at large is
potentially doing exactly once
processing in Druid so if you look at
the different open source
technology's out there they're all kind
of working towards a world where
streaming only ingestion streaming only
processing and streaming streaming only
like querying of data is all that you
need and you actually move beyond the
lambda architecture into into a
streaming only architecture I think
we're still a few years away from that
and various different open source
systems need to do their part to like
reach the end goal so like for the
commuters undred we're thinking a lot
about if that world exists and if open
source stream processors process exactly
once
what does Druid have to do you know to
ingest data once and not drop any data
so I think it will be exciting to see in
the next few years if we eventually
reach that world that gives a lot of
insight into a question which I should
have asked which is where do you see
druid going in the future right yeah so
I mean for the time being we really want
to make like we really want to focus on
the the core value add of druid which is
low latency queries low latency
injection to power applications so part
of that like part of what we want to do
is just make it much easier for
developers out there to be able to build
like data applications on top of druid
some some work that's related to that is
we got to make sure it a little bit
easier to set up and we really want to
make data ingestion easier and druid and
that goes back to this whole idea of
having you know one highly available
exactly once way of the streaming data
into druid
so we'll probably focusing a lot of our
efforts in the near future on that type
of work I guess one sort of interesting
thing to see is like a lot of search
infrastructure is starting to move more
in the analytic space and you can
foresee a future where you have sort of
one system to do maybe a legs and search
yeah I'm not a miracle we've all had
some shows about search engines and that
has come up there as well yeah I think I
think it'd be really interesting to see
like sort of analytics and search
converging into like one system the next
few years okay so to wrap things up if
people want to learn more about the
droid project or try it out how can they
you know there's we have a website it's
studio it has all the information we
have a Twitter feed as well the dirt
website has links to our community
forums and IRC you know a bunch of the
committers kind of just squat and IRC
and we answer questions from the
community and we ask a question the
forms as well so yeah check out the
website check out the Twitter handle
check out the forums and IRC people
would like to learn more about you or
get in touch with you where can they
find you I am sometimes on Twitter I
almost never use it I tweet entirely
from Druid splitter account you can
email me I spend a lot of time in the
forums so you know if you ask questions
there you'll probably embarrass for one
of them I'm also in the IRC a lot if you
want to chat directly great engineering
thank you very much thank you speaking
over thank you it was a pleasure yeah
that's awesome
thank you and for the listeners we would
love to hear from you about this show or
about the show in general you can send
us email to team at se - radio net find
us on Twitter at se radio on Facebook
LinkedIn or Google+ search for software
engineering radio or leave a comment on
our blog for software engineering radio
this has been Robert blumen thank you
for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on
Jane Google+ or Facebook you can also
email us at team at Etsy that's video
net this and all other episodes of se
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
2.5 license thanks again for your
support
[Music]
[Applause]